<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Something in answer to two late malitious libels of William Rogers; intituled, the sixth and eighth part of his (falsly so called) Christian-Quaker, &amp;c. : Being a further caution to Friends, to take heed of that treacherous spirit that is entered into William Rogers and his abettors. : Who under the profession of primitive truth, are betraying it to the world ... / Published for the clearing of truth against William Rogers's lies and slanders ... C.T.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Christopher, ca. 1615-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184889</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789424</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789424</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172734</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95027)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172734)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2647:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Something in answer to two late malitious libels of William Rogers; intituled, the sixth and eighth part of his (falsly so called) Christian-Quaker, &amp;c. : Being a further caution to Friends, to take heed of that treacherous spirit that is entered into William Rogers and his abettors. : Who under the profession of primitive truth, are betraying it to the world ... / Published for the clearing of truth against William Rogers's lies and slanders ... C.T.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Christopher, ca. 1615-1686.</author>
                  <author>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709. Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator. Part 6.</author>
                  <author>Rogers, William, d. ca. 1709. Christian-Quaker distinguished from the apostate &amp; innovator. Part 8.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Bringhurst ... at the Sign of the Book in Grace-church-Street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attribution to Christopher Taylor suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references in marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172734:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Something in ANSWER To Two late MALITIOUS LIBELS of William Rogers; Intituled, <hi>The Sixth and Eighth part of his</hi> (falſly ſo called) <hi>Chriſtian-Quaker,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Being a further Caution to FRIENDS, To take heed of that Treacherous Spirit that is entered into WILLIAM ROGERS and his Abettors.</p>
            <p>Who under the Profeſſion of <hi>Primitive Truth,</hi> are <hi>betraying it to the World,</hi> and puting <hi>truths Lambs</hi> into their <hi>Bearskins</hi> for the World to Worry, becauſe they have no power to do it themſelves, who have publiſhed their wicked Books in <hi>Askalon</hi> the <hi>fire of their Infamy;</hi> and have told it in <hi>Gath,</hi> the <hi>Wine Preſs,</hi> to preſs out their ſower Grapes to ſet the Peoples teeth on Edge againſt the Lambs of God.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Clearing of <hi>Truth</hi> againſt <hi>William Rogers</hi>'s <hi>Lies</hi> and <hi>Slanders,</hi> and for the Information of the ſimple-minded, that they may not be inſnared by the Crafts and Wiles of Satan through ſuch fallen Antichriſtian Inſtruments as <hi>William Rogers</hi> and ſuch as are Entered into the ſame Malitious Spirit with him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>C. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2 Tim. 3. v. 8.</hi>
                  </bibl> Now as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo do theſe alſo reſiſt the Truth, Men of Corrupt minds, Reprobate concerning the Faith.—</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>V. 9.</hi>
                  </bibl> But they ſhall proceed no further; their folly ſhall be manifeſt to all Men, as theirs alſo was.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>V. 13.</hi>
                  </bibl> But evil men and ſeducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Bringhurſt,</hi> Printer and Stationer, at the Sign of the <hi>Book</hi> in <hi>Grace-Church-Street.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb facs="tcp:172734:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:172734:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO William Rogers.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>William Rogers,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have read ſomething in thy two Books, called the ſixth and eighth part of thy Book, called, <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting upon me at a groſs abuſive rate, becauſe I withſtood thee in Print, in thy Printing that malicious Book called by thee, <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker, &amp;c.</hi> And good ground I had to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thee as I did: For reading in thy Book, I underſtood thy drift &amp; intent to be, to render dear <hi>G.F.</hi> by Name, &amp; ſeveral others dragged by their Names in thy Book, with my ſelf included, and indeed all Friends who are in Unity with us, who are the Church of Chriſt, <hi>to be <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators,</hi>
               </hi> and thy ſelf with thy Adherents, to be the <hi>Chriſtian-Quakers,</hi> in thy falſe ſence, as plainly appears in thy Book, which I ſuppoſe thou wilt not deny.</p>
            <p>So this being the true ſtate of the caſe, we muſt either ſubmit to thee, or thou, and thoſe of thy Spirit, to us. But that we are <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates</hi> or <hi>Innovators,</hi> (that is, <hi>Revolters, Backſliders from the Truth, deſerters of our Guide and Captain Chriſt Ieſus:</hi> And <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novators,</hi> or ſuch as <hi>bring in new things into the Church, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or contradict the true Government and State of it</hi>) we utterly deny, and reject thy falſe Charge, and all that are concerned with thee.—And my Charge from God upon thee is true: Thou art of a <hi>Rebellious Mind,</hi> and ſtandeſt up, as <hi>Korah</hi> and his Company did, againſt Gods faithful and true Servants, who have and do keep
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172734:3"/>
their Habitations in the Truth to this day: And thou art of a <hi>ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous Tongue, and void of a good Underſtanding.</hi> How long wilt thou pervert the <hi>Truth</hi> in thy gainſayings, and ſtand in oppoſition to the Lords power, and reject Gods pure Counſel to thee through his Servants, and their tender deſires for thee, which ſometimes have reached thy Conſcience! But take heed leſt thy <hi>Rum come,</hi> and there be none to help thee: And when thy work is over, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repentance, with <hi>Judas,</hi> thou go to thy proper place.</p>
            <p>What adoe thou makeſt becauſe I have quoted no particular ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence out of thy Book, but in the general as in my Title Page, and other places, I have given the Reader to underſtand, that the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of my Charge, againſt thee is in thy Book, called, <hi>The Chriſtian-Quaker, &amp;c.</hi> Theſe are my words in the Title Page: To Friends, <q>To take heed of that Treacherous Spirit that is entred into <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Rogers,</hi> and his Abettors; as appears in his Book falſely cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>The Chriſtian Quaker.</hi>
               </q> And if the ground of my Charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee be not the ground of thy Book, and in thy Book over and over; then I have erred and am not to be believed. But thou canſt not juſtly deny, nor any of thy Abettors, but that thou haſt rendred us aforementioned, to be both <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators;</hi> and if thou doſt deny it, thou doſt overthrow the foundation of thy Book: And none need to <hi>pin their Faith on my Sleeve</hi> to believe this; but in the Light of Chriſt to <hi>Read, See,</hi> and <hi>Believe for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> in this matter. And to thy wicked Book I refer the Reader, whether this be not the main Subject of it; and ſo is notorious falſe and blaſphemous. Read <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9. <hi>I know the Blaſphemy of them which ſay they are <hi>Iews</hi> and are not; but are of the Synagogue of</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan. This is become thy condition, who calleſt thy ſelf a <hi>Chriſtian Quaker;</hi> but indeed art of the <hi>Synagogue of Satan,</hi> that Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary.</p>
            <p>And what if I have neither particularly quoted <hi>Part</hi> nor <hi>Page</hi> of thy Book; yet what I affirm is true: Unto which, for proof of what I ſay, I refer the <hi>Reader</hi> to thy Book, and juſtifie my Charge againſt thee; and Charge thee with <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and <hi>gainſaying the Truth,</hi> and <hi>Power of God</hi> in his faithful Servants: For we Charge thee in the Preſence of God, and before his Angels and Men, to be a <hi>falſe Accuſer of the Brethren,</hi> and to be guided by a <hi>malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous evil Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172734:3"/>And now as for <hi>my not quoting Part and Page out of thy Book;</hi> I did not go about particularly to Anſwer thy Book, but <hi>to bear my Teſtimony againſt thee, not to be of God in that Spirit thou writ it.</hi> And in <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.15. is ſpoken by <hi>John</hi> of the Doctrine of the <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laitans</hi> which he <hi>hated,</hi> and quotes not <hi>what that Doctrine was,</hi> nor <hi>Chapter</hi> nor <hi>Verſe;</hi> and yet is not reflected on, as not to be believed in one word he ſpeaks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas thou quoteſt ſomething out of the third Page in my Book, and quarrel'ſt with the two laſt words <hi>[for ever]</hi> becauſe I ſay, <hi>To the Praiſe of his Name for ever;</hi> having before ſpoken of the Lords <hi>eminent Inſtruments in his Hand,</hi> as dear <hi>G. F.</hi> and others oppoſed by <hi>W. R.</hi> as <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators.</hi> Thou ſayeſt, by the words <hi>for ever, <hi>If I mean</hi>
               </hi> G. F. <hi>(that is to the Praiſe of</hi> G. F.'s <hi>Name for ever) Then thou ſayeſt I ſhould have added ſo and ſo,</hi> &amp;c. And ſo bringeſt in ſeveral <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fs</hi> and runneſt with thy <hi>Horns</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> But this is <hi>quibling,</hi> and <hi>ſcurrilous,</hi> and <hi>catching,</hi> according to the Nature of the Spirit thou art led by: For who will take it ſo? But to put all out of doubt for the ſake of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it is to be read, according to <hi>my Mind</hi> and <hi>Meaning, <hi>To the Praiſe of the Lords Name for ever.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>William,</hi> Theſe fooliſh things from a perverſe and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Airy Mind, thou haſt been Publiſhing and telling as in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askalon,</hi> that the uncircumciſed Prieſts and Profeſſors, and Rabble of unrighteous people may rejoyce. Is not this thy work?</p>
            <p>And really ſo, how canſt thou have a face to deny it? Doſt not thou ſeek to <hi>deſtroy</hi> our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Reputations in the Truth;</hi> by rendring us <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators?</hi> And what a Hurry and Pudder didſt thou and thine Adherents make, concerning <hi>John Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> how <hi>we went about to unminiſter him,</hi> becauſe we deſired him to <hi>return into the North, and firſt to be Reconciled to his Brethren, before he came and offered his Gift; otherwiſe he would go out in a contentious Spirit, to the ſowing of Strife and Sedition amongſt the Churches.</hi> Now conſider thy own work, who haſt eſpouſed his Cauſe, what havock thou makeſt to lay waſte the Heritage of God? not only according to thy Ability to go about to <hi>unminiſter</hi> Gods faithful Labourers, in the Work of his Goſpel; but alſo to <hi>unchriſtian</hi> them, by rendring them <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators.</hi> Oh! wicked Spirit and unbridled Tongue!</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172734:4"/>And what parallel is this? Thy Publiſhing of thy wicked Book againſt Gods People, as a common Adverſary to Gods Truth and his People, endeavouring to be believed in thy wicked work; and alſo as it were to curſe Gods Heritage from being his People and faithful Servants; if thou hadſt power according to thy will, as is too evident, by the proſecution of thy wicked Work; and ſo art in <hi>Balaam</hi>'s way? I ſay, what parallel is this, if all had been true what thou haſt written, (writing it in a malicious Spirit) to <hi>Pauls <hi>withſtanding</hi> Peter <hi>to his Face</hi> before all men;</hi> which is falſe: It is not <hi>[before all men]</hi> but <hi>[before them all]</hi> as is to be further ſhewn hereafter. Did <hi>Paul</hi> publiſh this to the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>all men</hi> to render him an <hi>Apoſtate</hi> and <hi>Innovator,</hi> and all of his Spirit, who had Unity with him, as thou haſt done us? Nay it is manifeſt, that <hi>Peter</hi> received and owned the plain-dealing and love of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Paul,</hi> and felt it to come from the Spirit of Love and true-heartedneſs to him: And it was ſo far from making a breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, that it more nearly united them.</p>
            <p>And afterwards <hi>Peter</hi> very affectionately ſpeaks of his beloved Brother <hi>Paul,</hi> and of his Epiſtles, <hi>in which</hi> (ſays he) <hi>are ſome things hard lo be underſtood; which they that are unlearned and unſtable, wreſt (as they do alſo the other Scriptures) unto their own deſtruction,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.15, 16. As thou haſt endeavoured to pervert the plain dealing of <hi>Paul</hi> with <hi>Peter</hi> to ſerve thy own turn, and thy falſe end in Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us to the World as <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators,</hi> &amp;c. And what if this be now made publick? it is a work quite contrary to thine, and from another Spirit, and to another end. O <hi>William!</hi> If thou couldſt but ſee thy work and repent of it, how glad ſhould I be! I have pitied thee, and wiſhed thee better imployment.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou reflects upon me in the ſixth part, <hi>p.</hi> 21. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>That I act like ſuch as have had their Education at <hi>Bilingſgate,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Scolds,</hi> rather than under the Roof of <hi>ſober Families.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed be God I act againſt thee, as the Lord does give me a good underſtanding; and ſee thee to be of a wicked Spirit, in <hi>Ko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah's</hi> way and State of Rebellion, and of <hi>Cain</hi>'s murtherous Line (I mean ſpiritually) and how impudent art thou, to compare <hi>my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation</hi> with the <hi>Education of the Scolds at Bilingſgate?</hi> I have had for this thirty years, or thereabouts, my <hi>Education</hi> in the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Truth, and always was, in thy beſt condition, thy Elder in it;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172734:4"/>
and have never yet deſerved thy baſe language concerning my <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation:</hi> And before I was convinced of the Truth, I was of bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter behaviour than thou now art; for I then loved good and honeſt people, who feared the Lord, and wrought Righteouſneſs in their day and Generation; and ſought and enquired after the knowledge of the Lord from my young and tender years; but thou art in a Rebellious State againſt Gods faithful Servants. Alas <hi>William!</hi> is this thy work, to abuſe <hi>Me</hi> and many grave <hi>Ancients</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who have kept their Habitations in the Truth?—Herein I may a little boaſt to ſtop thy mouth: Bring forth the Perſon who, this thirty years laſt paſt, can tax my Life and <hi>Converſation,</hi> or <hi>Education;</hi> that I have not had my Education ſo in the Truth, that I have been in my Life what I have Doctrinally Preached forth: I ſpeak this to the Praiſe of Gods Grace, and teſtifie in the fear of God againſt thy ſlanderous tongue. But it is like thee, who art guided by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly and rebellious Spirit, who haſt corrupted thy manners by thy evil words; who art turned againſt the Truth, and thy Tongue is at liberty to abuſe thoſe that have kept their Habitations in it. Thou art a quarrelſom man, and thy impudence is ſo great, that thou endeavoureſt to ſupplant the Righteous ſeed, and abuſe Gods <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Labourers</hi> in his <hi>Vineyard,</hi> by rendring them as <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators,</hi> and ſo art miſchievous in thy undertakings; and we know thou art a <hi>falſe Accuſer,</hi> and thou endeavoureſt to ſtop the courſe of our Teſtimonies, that we may not be believed as <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Miniſters,</hi> by thy falſe inſinuations, who would prejudice both Friends and others againſt us, to ſtop their Ears from hearing the Truth; declared by us. O wicked envious Spirit, do thy worſt: What canſt thou do with all thy power? Gods pure ſimplicity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing kept unto amongſt his people, they eaſily diſcern thee to be an <hi>Apoſtate</hi> and <hi>faln Spirit,</hi> if ever thou hadſt a condition in the Truth. And if ever thou hadſt, then waſt thou but a <hi>Novice</hi> in it, and yet haſt taken upon thee a miſchievous work, to run out with thy Horns againſt ſuch as <hi>G. F. G. W.</hi> and my ſelf, and many others, rendring us <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators.</hi> But we truly comprehend thee to be got up into preſumption, lifted up with pride, and art fallen into the condemnation of the Devil.</p>
            <p>And therefore it is that thou art become malicious, and haſt not kept thy firſt State in the Truth, but haſt left that habitation ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172734:5"/>
to thy meaſure which thou hadſt in it: And now thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareſt in thy wickedneſs againſt the Living God, and in this State, except thou canſt find a place of Repentance, thou art reſerved in the everlaſting Chains of Darkneſs unto the Judgment of the Great day.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou reflects and deſpiſes that <hi>good Government of Chriſt,</hi> that the God of Heaven hath erected and eſtabliſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us by his Spirit and Power, the ground and foundation of which, in my <hi>Epiſtle of Caution,</hi> I have in meaſure laid down, I believe to the ſatisfaction of all innocent Friends that fear God: Yet thy foul Spirit is ſo offended at this work, that thou art evil af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected towards it, under the colour of <hi>Impoſitions</hi> and <hi>Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and <hi>forcing a Conformity upon Conſcience vefore Conviction and without Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto which I anſwer, <hi>Without Faith it is impoſſible to pleaſe God:</hi> And therefore we perſwade men, by the force of Truth and the Word of the Lord, to be reconciled to every thing that is good, as to <hi>good Order</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> and not to ſtand in oppoſition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>And a great clamour thou makeſt about <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and filleſt people full of ſtories of this kind, and rendreſt us little better in theſe matters than <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Popiſhly affected:</hi> And yet notwithſtanding doſt not ſet down what all theſe <hi>Orders</hi> are: Thou malitious man, begin from firſt to laſt, and tell ſuch to whom thou Writes and Prints, what all theſe <hi>Orders</hi> are, thou ſo openſt thy Mouth againſt: If they be <hi>good in themſelves,</hi> as ſome of thy Friends have ſaid and confeſſed, therefore why not practicable, and why ſhould they be oppoſed? But ye are in confuſion.</p>
            <p>Should we not endeavour that every ſimple-hearted perſon may be informed and truly Inſtructed in that which is <hi>Pure, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, Good,</hi> and <hi>Commendable,</hi> that all things may be done in <hi>good Order,</hi> by the ſpirit of God, to the praiſe of the Name of the Great God, who is the God of <hi>Order</hi> and not of Confuſion or Anarchy.</p>
            <p>They that plead for <hi>Liberty</hi> Contrary to the pure Spirit, Life and Power of Jeſus Chriſt, are out of the Faith, and not faithful to God. And in that ſtate they are blind and Ignorant of Gods way, and Truth in this his Goſpel Diſpenſation: And ſo they become
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172734:5"/>
wilful Oppoſers, of that which is good in a Diſobedient mind, and ſo call <hi>Good Evil,</hi> and <hi>Evil Good,</hi> And that <hi>Government</hi> that is erected by the Eternal God in the hearts of his people, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe and contemn, becauſe they are not in a Condition to Anſwer it, becauſe of their ſinful diſobedience, and love Darkneſs more than Light.</p>
            <p>And if People be <hi>Simple-minded,</hi> We know the <hi>faithful-hearted</hi> that fear God, into whom he gives a good underſtanding, will endeavour to inform ſuch, as at any time may <hi>conſcientiouſly</hi> ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple any thing in this matter; And we ſay, <hi>None ſhould oppoſe, who do not ſee, and who do not believe thoſe things, which others both truly ſee, and to be of God,</hi> leſt they fight like blind men, but thou in thy <hi>wilful mind</hi> teacheſt Rebellion, and to make the minds of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-hearted, evill affected with the <hi>Government of God</hi> and Chriſt Jeſus. Which he hath, and is ſtill Eſtableſhing amongſt us, and like <hi>Iannes</hi> and <hi>Iambres,</hi> thy mind is corrupted to oppoſe the Truth, <hi>being Reprobate or of no Judgment concerning the Faith.</hi> For they that are faithful to God know us and our work who are his Servants and Miniſters through his Grace Excerciſed in his Work, and Service; And that we are neither <hi>Apoſtates</hi> nor <hi>Innovators</hi> (for that's thy own condition) as thy lying Tongue would Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate—And that <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Grder,</hi> we have Eſtableſhed by the Lord amongſt us, is ſo far from the <hi>Spirit of Antichriſt</hi> in the Eſtableſhment of it, that it is no leſs than the <hi>product of Gods Power,</hi> and <hi>Heavenly Wisdom,</hi> which is <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>peaceable</hi> from above. But thy <hi>Folly</hi> will be fully Mannifeſt, and thy <hi>ſhame</hi> will appear, though thou wouldſt hide it, by endeavouring groſly to abuſe ſuch <hi>Ancients</hi> in <hi>Jſrael,</hi> as God hath clothed with his Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Righteouſneſs. I ſay, thy ſhame will appear, and thy work of Wickedneſs will be made manifeſt to all the Simple-hearted, who in their Souls truely deſire to be tought by the Lord that they may be truly Eſtabliſhed in his Righteouſneſs.</p>
            <p>And whereas, In thy Eigth Part (page 11.) thou haſt theſe words; <hi>And if this <hi>ſmall Tract,</hi> as well as other <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> of <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy</hi> and <hi>Innovation,</hi> become as ſo many Darts to pierce the bowels of that Cauſe eſpowſed by thoſe nameleſs perſons, terming themſelves <hi>the ſecond Days Meeting,</hi> even as an Arrow ſhot at an Adventure, pierced <hi>Ahab</hi> between the Joints of his Harnaſs when diſguiſed to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172734:6"/>
ſave himſelf, then let us ſay, bleſſed be the God of our Solvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>William,</hi> thy Drift &amp; Intent, as what thou aimeſt at, we clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceive, and it is eaſy ſo to do; For the Darts thou ſhooteſt, thou aimeſt at Gods ſervants, <hi>the Second Days Meeting,</hi> to pierce the bowels of their cauſe, which cauſe is the <hi>Cauſe of God,</hi> and they are and have been concerned againſt thee, to bear Teſtimony againſt that Graceleſs ungodly Spirit with which thy heart is poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that ſo the Truth being eſpouſed by them, may ſtill prevail over thy Lyes and baſe Slanders in thy wicked Works, who careſt little what thou doeſt, or ſayeſt, if thou canſt but make the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> of it, who are exerciſed in the Work and ſervice of God, <hi>Odious;</hi> But all the ſimple-hearted, who read that Book In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titled, <hi>The Accuſer,</hi> &amp;c. may eaſily ſee thy Lies, and Slanders detected, and thy wicked heart, to thy ſhame, made Manifeſt, that thou mayſt be read as thou art, in thy own Nature, <hi>viz.</hi> As an <hi>Apoſtate</hi> and <hi>Common Adverſary</hi> to Gods Truth, and his faithful Servants, who have kept their habitations in the Truth, and ſtand againſt thy deſign, which is wicked—Thou ſheweſt thou art of a Murthering ſpirit, with thy Arrows; but they are turned back upon thee again, to pierce thy own Bowels, Read <hi>Pſalms the</hi> 11.2. Where thou mayſt ſee into thy Work and condition. For Loe, the Wicked bend their Bow; they make ready their Arrow upon the ſtring, that they may privily ſhoot at the Upright in heart, but thou haſt miſt the Mark, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> thou ſayſt Part 8. Page. 10. <hi>Our Ancient Friends J. S. and J. W. when Articled againſt for not acting againſt their conſcience,</hi> &amp;c. And Page 3. thou ſpeakeſt of <hi>J. W.</hi> and <hi>J. S.</hi> again, and Page 6. thou ſayeſt, <hi>There is no ground either from the Scriptures of Truth without, or the Light of Chriſt within us, to believe that any Chriſtian Profeſſor can in Truth affirm, that there are outward Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, and Orders given forth by the Spirit of God through any one or more mortal men in this our Day, which others ought to obey or follow, whether they ſee it their Duty or no, ſo far</hi> W. R. Anſwers. The Inſinuation of our giving out <hi>Inſtructions <hi>to be practiſed, whilſt people do not ſee them their Duty,</hi>
               </hi> is a falſe Inſinuation; for <hi>Inſtructions of Duty</hi> may be given out before they ſee them ſuch; as believing that God will by his Light diſcover to them their Duty there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, if they be not obſtinate, that they may practiſe them in the Light.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:172734:6"/>Perſons not ſeeing their duty, does not make that voyd which is in itſelf their duty; Nor yet ought mens blindneſs to debar true Miniſters from Preaching to them what is their Duty; for many ſee it not their Duty, to believe the light of Chriſt in them, and yet it muſt be Preached to them, to open their eyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then doth it not plainly appear, that <hi>I. Wilkinſon,</hi> and <hi>W. Rogers,</hi> are not in the light of Chriſt, and Spirit of God; but are as yet blind, and do not ſee that which is given forth from the Light and Spirit of God to be their <hi>Duty</hi> to Obey and follow? And ſuch by <hi>W. Rogers</hi> muſt be Accounted <hi>Honourable, Elders</hi> and <hi>Preachers;</hi> And yet in his Sixth Part, Page 12. tells us, <hi>The Kingdom of God ſtands in Righteouſneſs, and Peace, and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and tells us again in his Sixth Part. (Page 3.) of his <hi>Inward peace with the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. and in his Second Page, Part, 8. there he ſpeaks of the <hi>Government of Chriſt, who alone is Lord over the Conſcience;</hi> and Page 10. Part 6. he tells us, He is <hi>breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Lord of Heaven, That we and</hi> G. F. <hi>may be humbled be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord, and</hi> G. F. <hi>in Particular, that High and Lofty one, may not utterly fall,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What a mad Prayer is this! how canſt thou be at <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>breath unto the Lord,</hi> and be thus <hi>Wicked?</hi> for thy Prayers are an Abomination to the Lord. And thou haſt not only Judged <hi>G. F,</hi> but (as thou ſcoffingly ſaiſt) <hi>his party</hi> alſo, to be <hi>Apoſtates;</hi> that is, ſuch as have bleſſed Unity with him in the Truth, which is the whole Body of Friends, who have kept their Habitations in the Living Truth and Faith of Gods Elect, which thou art gone from.</p>
            <p>And by what Spirit doſt thou pretend thou haſt Peace with God, and breatheſt to God, and telleſt of his Kingdom; and yet art blind, and doſt not ſee its thy Duty to obey and follow that which is given forth from the Spirit of God? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How can thy Spirit and the Spirit of thoſe, thou termeſt thy <hi>Honourable Brethren,</hi> be accounted any otherwiſe then a <hi>looſe fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And doth W. R. and thoſe that Encouraged him to publick his confuſed Books, ſtuffed full of <hi>Contradictions,</hi> and with a Rabble of <hi>falſe charges</hi> (as hath been ſhewn in other <hi>Anſwers</hi> in Print) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that they proceeded from Gods Spirit, when he doth not ſee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172734:7"/>
it to be <hi>his Duty, <hi>to Obey that which is given forth from the Spirit of God?</hi>
               </hi> are you all of his Mind?</p>
            <p>And he ſaith, Speaking of the Unction, <hi>That by it all things are known.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet he doth not ſee it his Duty to Obey that which is given forth from the Spirit of God: For this is applied to <hi>William Rogers. J. Story, J. Wilkinſon,</hi> and <hi>their Followers,</hi> for he doth not mention any others, who are thus Blind, that they do not ſee; <hi>for we who are the Members of that Body which Chriſt is the Head of, do ſee it is <hi>our Duty</hi> to <hi>Obey</hi> that which is given forth from the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> in our day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Do we not Read that under the Dipenſation of the Law, which came by <hi>Moſes, the Prieſts lips were to preſerve the Peoples Knowledge, and to be Inſtructers to the People in all things pertaining to that Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, that the People might not be Ignorant of the Law of God, but might fully know it; And where they doubted in any thing, that Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood was to Compleat their Knowledge in it, that they might not plead <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> in any thing contained in the Law to be done,</hi> for God was able by his <hi>Spirit,</hi> then both <hi>Immidiatly</hi> and <hi>Inſtrumentally</hi> by his <hi>Prieſthood,</hi> appointed under that Diſpenſation to Inſtruct them fully; and none then could ſay, <hi>they did not ſee, or they did not believe what was</hi> the <hi>mind of God</hi> under that Diſpenſation. But thoſe that wilfully ſtopped their <hi>Ears,</hi> and ſhut their <hi>Eyes,</hi> leaſt they ſhould <hi>hear</hi> and <hi>ſee,</hi> underſtand and <hi>obey</hi> the will of God, who <hi>Rebel'd againſt the Spirit.</hi> And ſuch came to be hardined in their Sins, and <hi>Rebel</hi> againſt the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>deſpiſe</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> of it, as <hi>Korah</hi> and his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany in the <hi>Conſpiracy</hi> againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Much more now in our day under the clear <hi>Goſpel Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> may the <hi>Iſrael of God</hi> be fully <hi>Inſtructed</hi> both Immediately and <hi>Inſtrumentally</hi> by his Spirit, in all things pertaining to the Doctrine and Diſcipline of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goſpel Government,</hi> that their hearts may be ſubject thereunto: and they need not plead <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and ſay, <hi>I ſee not this,</hi> or <hi>I believe not this,</hi> and, <hi>If I do this, or Obey t'otheir, it will be a blind Obedience, and I ſhall do it without Faith or ſight.</hi> I ſay, none need plead thus, and upon this ground, and with their <hi>blind Minds</hi> and <hi>dark Underſtandings</hi> in their <hi>Diſobedience, oppoſe</hi> Gods People in what they both <hi>ſee and believe to be given forth by his Spirit.</hi> For Chriſt hath enlightned
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172734:7"/>
them all, and hath poured his Spirit upon all Fleſh, that they may <hi>ſee and perceive that which is given forth from the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore we do affirm, that every Imprejudiced ſimple-harted Friend, waiting and following on to know the Lord in his <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> will grow up in the <hi>Faith,</hi> and not oppoſe the <hi>Faithful</hi> in their <hi>Faithfulneſs</hi> towards God, in what he makes known of his Will. And ſo the <hi>Simple-minded,</hi> will mind the Lord and his power, which will preſerve them in Unity and fellowſhip with the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the <hi>Members of Chriſt in</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Light</hi> according to their growth in the Truth, and if at any time there be any <hi>Conſcientious Scrupling</hi> concerning any thing as to matter of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> or <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> or any thing elſe, they will be deſirous and willing to <hi>Ask Counſil of the Lord,</hi> and in Gentleneſs and Meekneſs of his <hi>Faithful Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> in <hi>ſinſerity</hi> without <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> as the <hi>Corinthians</hi> did to <hi>Paul,</hi> who <hi>anſwered them cencerning the things they had wrote to him,</hi> that they might be Convinced and helped in matters pertaining to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And where did ever the <hi>Jews</hi> ſay to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, <hi>They were not convinced, and did not ſee if their Duty to follow and obey that which they declared from the Lord to them?</hi> And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo where did ever the Diſciples of Chriſt ſay, <hi>We are not convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and do not ſee it our Duty to follow and obey that which thou Commandeſt us.</hi> And foraſmuch as it is on Record, that the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and the <hi>Elders</hi> wrote their <hi>Orders</hi> and <hi>Decrees,</hi> and <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions</hi> to the Churches, where did ever the Churches and true be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers tell the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and the <hi>Elders <hi>they did not ſee, nor beliebe, and had not Faith in their words, and therefore it was not their Duty to Obey that which they writ, and ſpoke to them from the Lord, by his Spirit;</hi>
               </hi> but called it <hi>Impoſition,</hi> and <hi>blind Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> this always was a marke of the <hi>falſe Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> who oppoſed the true; and it was and is the Devil that did, and does blind People now, that they do not ſee their Duty to God, to do what he commands them.</p>
            <p>Are the <hi>Ranters</hi> excuſable, becauſe they ſay, <hi>they do not ſee or believe the wickedneſs they commit to be ſin or evil?</hi> Will this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them in the the day of Judgment? take warning and take heed.</p>
            <p>Muſt not the <hi>ſecrets of Men be Judged by Jeſus Chriſt, according to the Goſpell, which is Preached to, or in every Creature under Heaven?</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:172734:8"/>
And canſt thou, and thine Abettors be excuſed in your wilfulneſs, and wicked rebellion againſt God, and his People, under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, <hi>that you do not ſee nor believe?</hi> Nay, <hi>William,</hi> thou and you are ſeen, and your wicked work is weighed in the Ballance of Truth, and found too light, and <hi>Woe</hi> and <hi>Miſery</hi> from God will be your Portion, except you <hi>Repent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your Nakedneſs doth appear for want of anointing your eyes with eye-ſalve, that you might ſee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For truly, ſince you went from the Light of Chriſt, by which you were convinced; by which all God's People are now at this day kept in Unity; I do plainly ſee with that eye-ſalve God hath given me, that you are got into a Spirit of <hi>Rudeneſs, Lightneſs, Scornfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>deſpiſing thoſe that truly fear the Lord;</hi> ſo that it is enough to convince every ſober-minded perſon, what Spirit you are led and acted by, that they may ſee with the Light of Chriſt, how you are fallen from the <hi>pure truth of the Goſpel</hi> into <hi>Looſeneſs,</hi> like ſo many <hi>Way-marks for God's people to ſhun,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> Thou makeſt a great Pudder and muddleſt thy head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our <hi>Orders</hi> in part 8. p. 5. and twice in pag. 6. And about <hi>outward preſcriptions</hi> in the ſame Page twice; and pag. 10. there thou art at it again, and ſpeakeſt of <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Preſcriptions</hi> twice over; then pag. 13. thou art at it again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But <hi>William,</hi> why doſt thou make ſuch a confuſed noiſe about our <hi>Orders,</hi> as though thy Head was amazed! And doſt ſo worry them with thy muddled Head, that thou haſt not been able to give a perfect liſt of them, (though it has been of thee demanded, <hi>What thoſe <hi>Orders</hi> are, that our Friends have <hi>impoſed</hi> upon you</hi>) For with thy own muddled <hi>Head</hi> thou thinkeſt to <hi>mud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle</hi> others <hi>Heads</hi> with thy making a noiſe about our <hi>Orders, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions, Decrees</hi> and <hi>Government;</hi> but neither thou nor <hi>J. S.</hi> nor <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi> have yet given a full and particular Account of them, <hi>what they are,</hi> and ſtated them aright, with the <hi>day when,</hi> and the <hi>Year</hi> they were given forth, that people might have ſeen them, together with a Catalogue of <hi>thy own, I. Wilkinſon</hi>'s and <hi>I. Story</hi>'s <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Orders, <hi>what they are;</hi>
               </hi> thou ſhouldſt have brought them forth, that people might have ſeen them, and been able to judge of them. So give over thy making a <hi>Noiſe,</hi> and <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouring,</hi> and <hi>Brawling</hi> againſt <hi>our Orders, Preſcriptions</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:172734:8"/>
as long as thou doſt not diſcover them all to the people what they are; that people may not be deceived by thee; and pin their Faith on thy Sleeve; for in this thy empty work, thou haſt but been beating the Air.</p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>Fruits of a Careleſs, Looſe, Libertine, Dark Spirit, W. R.</hi> with all his <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'s</hi> in all his Writings hath not proved againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> but hath manifeſted them to be the <hi>Fruits of his own Spirit,</hi> whoſe <hi>Tongue is become no ſlander,</hi> nor words of any Credit with them that fear the Lord.</p>
            <p>And <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi> and <hi>W. Rogers</hi> have not anſwer'd <hi>G. F</hi>'s Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion yet (though <hi>W. R.</hi> be at it again in his 8th part, pag. 8.) viz. <hi>Whether or no an Heavenly Member of Chriſt's Body (<hi>that is,</hi>
               </hi> ſuch as are born again of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and of the <hi>Immortal ſeed</hi> by the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God) <hi>turns to Duſt, Yea or Nay?</hi>
               </hi> For <hi>G. F</hi>'s Query was not about an <hi>Earthly Member,</hi> nor an Earthly Corruptible Body; but an <hi>Heavenly Member.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Part 8. pag. 2, 3. <hi>W. R.</hi> ſays, <hi>It's the duty of ſome,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to pin their Faith on the ſleeves of</hi> C. T. &amp;c. Again, <hi>This ſmall Tract is now written for the ſakes of ſuch among the people called</hi> Quakers, <hi>as are not yet Principle'd to pin their Faith upon other mens ſleeves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Are not the ſpreaders and the ſellers of <hi>W. R</hi>'s malitious Books, the <hi>pinners of their Faith upon his ſleeve?</hi> And yet they are ſo confuſed, that they will not ſtand by him in it. But it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways my Judgment to Judge ſuch, as Pin their Faith upon thy ſleeve, or <hi>J. S</hi>'s, or <hi>J. W</hi>'s, or upon any elſe. For the Faith of God's Elect ſtands in Chriſt, the Author and Finiſher of it. And what need was there, that any one that reads my Book againſt thee, ſhould pin their Faith on my ſlieve?</p>
            <p>But <hi>W. R.</hi> haſt not thou Judged us often over in thy malitious ſlanderous Book, to be Apoſtates and Innovators? Was not this a juſt ground for me to declare thee to be of <hi>Korahs</hi> Spirit, and of <hi>Cains</hi> Line? And if thou haſt not in thy Book rendred us ſuch, as <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Innovators</hi> (unto which I refer the Reader) then clear thy ſelf if thou canſt; or elſe the Burthen of my words in my Teſtimony againſt thee in that Spirit, thou writ that Book, muſt certainly lie upon thee. And herein I have not wronged thee, I affirm it, and ſtill charge thee in the ſame true Judgment, to be of <hi>Korahs,</hi> and <hi>Cains</hi> Line, to be ſealed down under Eternal Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172734:9"/>
and Condemnation, from God for ever, except thou Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; and we ſtand over thee in the Authority of God's Power, and of ſuch as Abet to thee, and adhere to thee in that Malitious, Proud and Lofty Spirit, thou art entred into.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> ſaith, part 8. pag. 5. <hi>That 'twas ſafer to have a Dependency on this meaſure (of Chriſts Light) in our ſelves, than to have an Eye out to the meaſures of others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hath not <hi>W. R.</hi> ſhewed his Darkneſs and theirs, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged him to Print his Book? For can any ſee the meaſure of the Spirit of Chriſt, and his Light in others, but by the meaſure of the Spirit of God in themſelves, in which they come into Unity? But where did ever either I or any of our faithful Brethren bring any to look, and have a Dependency upon the Meaſure in others, and neglect the meaſure of the Spirit of God in themſelves, by which they ſhould be guided to become the Sons and Daughters of God? This was never our Principle, but thou wouldſt inſinuate ſuch a thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> And in Part 8. pag. 10. thou ſpeakeſt of <hi>a Viſible man to be an Eye to ſee for the reſt of the Body;</hi> and pag. 11. thou bringeſt the ſame; and Part 6. pag. 16. thou art muddling thy head again about the ſame thing, and telleſt of a late Doctrine, <hi>viz. Have your Eye to the Brethren.</hi> And ſayſt further, <hi>The ſubſtance of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine hath of late been publiſh'd alſo in Publick Meetings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>As in the Natural Body the Eye is placed to ſee for all the reſt of the Members, ſo alſo in the Spiritual; and hath been explained ſo, as it hath been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times taken, that</hi> G. F. <hi>is an Eye for the whole Body, and other times, as if ſome other Perſons were an Eye for a Meeting,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But who have publiſh'd theſe Doctrines (whom thou haſt ſo backbited in Print) thou haſt not named their names; ſo muſt I <hi>pin my Faith on thy ſlieve</hi> for the proof thereof. But hath not my <hi>Caution to the ſimple-hearted, that they ſhould not be deceived by thy ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſlanderous Book,</hi> tormented thee and thy Spirit, becauſe of thy wicked Works? And doth not <hi>W. R.</hi> think himſelf to be <hi>an Eye to his Brethren?</hi> And doth he not take himſelf to be an <hi>Eye for</hi> John Story, J. Wilkinſon, and the reſt of the <hi>Seperate Company?</hi> And have not they made him their <hi>Eye,</hi> and <hi>Tongue,</hi> and <hi>Mouth</hi> to Publiſh their Writings, and Words, and <hi>their ſilly falſe Certifficate?</hi> Or is their <hi>Body</hi> without an <hi>Eye?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:172734:9"/>But the living Members, which are the Church, and the <hi>Body</hi> o <hi>Chriſt</hi> which he is <hi>head</hi> of, he hath given a Spiritual Eye unto; for he is their <hi>Eye</hi> by his <hi>Light</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> and <hi>without him we can do nothing:</hi> By which <hi>Light</hi> all Members do <hi>ſee</hi> for themſelves, and to edifie one another in the moſt Holy Faith.—And I would have all people to have an <hi>Eye</hi> from <hi>Chriſt in themſelves,</hi> that they may <hi>ſee</hi> both thy Spirit, and thy Books, which many do now more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee, than before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> ſaith, in Part 6. pag. 3, 4. <hi>When I conſider what Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of the weaker ſort of people, are apt to be deceived, by Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing Shadows inſtead of Subſtance, and Lies inſtead of Truth,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>it hath been one motive amongſt others, occaſioned me once more to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in Print.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Hath not <hi>W. R.</hi> appeared here to make the <hi>weaker,</hi> and them that are <hi>apt to be deceived</hi> (to <hi>believe</hi> him to be a <hi>ſtrong man</hi>) and an <hi>Eye to ſee for them,</hi> that which they are not able to ſee for themſelves, nor help themſelves who are <hi>weak?</hi> ſo doth not he pretend here <hi>to ſee for them,</hi> and <hi>to be a ſtrength to them?</hi> which he ſays, <hi>Hath been one motive amongſt others, occaſioning him once more to appear in Print?</hi> ſo hath he not made himſelf a <hi>Seer,</hi> or an <hi>Overſeer</hi> here among <hi>others;</hi> which thing in effect, he Judges in the <hi>Body of Chriſt,</hi> of which <hi>Body</hi> we are.</p>
            <p>Now doth not here <hi>W. R.</hi> confound himſelf? For why ſhould not thoſe <hi>Weak, hear for themſelves,</hi> and <hi>ſee for themſelves,</hi> with the Light and Grace of Chriſt, which thou <hi>W. R.</hi> confeſſeſt to be <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient?</hi> And doſt not thou ſpeak of an <hi>Unction within them, by which all things were known?</hi> Part 8. pag. 11.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Is not this the occaſion that thou once more appearedſt in Print,</hi> that thoſe Weak, and ſuch as are apt to be deceived, may look at thy Writings? For thou doſt not ſay, they ſhould try thy Writings by the Light, and Grace of Chriſt within them, (in the Third and Fourth Pages, Part Six.) But is it not really thy mind, that they ſhould believe thee, to ſee for them, and help them, and to pin their Faith on thy Slieve? If not, to what end is thy Writing? For if thou ſeeſt neither for their Body, nor for the ſeparate Meeting; what doth all thy Scribling then ſignifie?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> Part 8. pag. 10. <hi>That the Grace of God is ſufficient, and that every one is to be left to their own meaſure.</hi> Thou needſt not tell us that, who obey it.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:172734:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:172734:10"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:172734:11"/>And whereas thou goeſt over and over in thy Book, telling us of <hi>G. F</hi>'s <hi>Party;</hi> but this is from thy malicious foul Spirit. We are not ſuch a Party as thou wouldſt inſinuate, but are for Chriſt, and all his Believers in the <hi>Light,</hi> which is the Life in Chriſt Jeſus, before <hi>Parties</hi> were: And that in the Light, Grace and Spirit of Chriſt, we might all exalt Chriſt, both in <hi>Males</hi> and <hi>Females,</hi> and by it we may know him to Reign in all our hearts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> And whereas thou keepeſt a <hi>Railing</hi> againſt the <hi>Second Days Meeting</hi> in ſeveral places in thy Book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I muſt tell thee, the leaſt <hi>Babe</hi> in Chriſt, that is of that <hi>Meeting,</hi> hath an Underſtanding with the Light and Spirit of Chriſt, to <hi>ſee</hi> over thy <hi>foul Spirit,</hi> and its Works: and God hath given them the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Judgment to Judge them both. And thou ſhalt proceed no further, but art detected, and thy <hi>Folly</hi> will be made manifeſt to all men that hear or ſee thy Books. And the God of Heaven and Earth hath ſuffered thee a while, that when thou haſt <hi>run</hi> thy <hi>Race,</hi> he may faſten his <hi>Hook</hi> in thy <hi>Jaws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how dare <hi>W. R.</hi> Part 8. pag. 6. ſay, <hi>That the Second Days Meeting is Guilty of the like Crime, of that nameleſs</hi> Book, that <hi>W. P.</hi> anſwered? Whereas <hi>Ellis Hooks</hi> his name was ſet to the Book, on the behalf of the <hi>Second-Days</hi>-Meeting; whoſe Credit did go as far as <hi>W. R</hi>'s, and farther, among them that fear God. And others alſo of us do own it, and will ſtand by it.</p>
            <p>And <hi>W. R.</hi> Part 6. pag. 9. ſpeaks, <hi>Of</hi> Saul<hi>'s hearkning to</hi> Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el <hi>the Prophet,</hi> &amp;c. '<hi>Which he thinks, ſhould be a warning to</hi> G. F. <hi>and others of his Party, to hearken unto the Word of the Lord that came through his Servant</hi> John Wilkinſon, <hi>on the Twentieth Day of the Sixth Month,</hi> 1675. <hi>on this wiſe,</hi> viz. <hi>To Repent and turn from your Proceedings, and leave Gods people to the Order of his Goſpel and Command; and that if they would not, then the Lord himſelf would break them, and turn them one againſt another about their Orders;</hi> ſo far <hi>W. R.</hi> of <hi>John Wilkinſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But neither <hi>W. R</hi>'s, nor <hi>J. W</hi>'s Words do anſwer the Light of the Spirit of God in our Conſciences, to believe his words, as the <hi>word</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> which proceeded from his <hi>Imaginations,</hi> and <hi>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perverſe Spirit.</hi> For all the Believers in the Light, which are the Children of Light, are in the Glorious <hi>Order</hi> of his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> the <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Command;</hi> and others are exhorted to it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:172734:11"/>And <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi> might ſee, (and thou alſo if thou and he will believe Truth) that he is a <hi>falſe Prophet;</hi> and his <hi>falſe Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> is come upon himſelf. For how many hath the Lord broken off from them in the <hi>North,</hi> and alſo in the <hi>South?</hi> And through thy Wicked <hi>Printings,</hi> many have come to ſee with the Light of Chriſt your Wicked Spirit, and its Work: And eſpecially when they ſee <hi>J. S</hi>'s and <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi>'s <hi>Orders</hi> of giving power to meet; and thoſe that would not take them, but would meet without their Power and Orders, were called <hi>Uſurpers of Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And many of theſe <hi>Simple-hearted,</hi> which were enſnared by <hi>Subſcribing</hi> to them, are come off from them, and have given <hi>Certificates</hi> againſt <hi>J. Story</hi> and <hi>J. Wilkinſon,</hi> which <hi>W. R.</hi> ſaith, <hi>It was an Endeavouring to uncover the pretended Nakedneſs of them,</hi> (to wit, his Brothers or Brethren) <hi>ſending Certificates abroad thereof, Spread amongſt Friends and Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I do underſtand, that thoſe <hi>Enemies</hi> were ſuch, as <hi>J. W.</hi> and <hi>J. S.</hi> had deceived and drawn into a Seperation, or did Abet them; and the <hi>Friends</hi> were the faithful that kept to Chriſt their head, and did not follow <hi>J. S.</hi> nor <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi> in their Sepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And to ſuch they were ſent, that they might ſee, how they had been betrayed; and as a Warning to others, that they might not be deceived as thou hadſt been. So the <hi>Spreading</hi> of thoſe <hi>Certificates</hi> according to the mind of thoſe, who had been ſeduc'd into a joyning with the <hi>Seperate Meeting,</hi> and were brought off through Gods Great Mercy, was to the honour of God, and good <hi>Caution</hi> to others. Neither were they <hi>Printed;</hi> but ſent amongſt <hi>Friends</hi> and thy own <hi>Company</hi> who are gone into Enmity, and ſo become <hi>Enemies.</hi> This is no Parallel to the <hi>Printing</hi> and <hi>Spread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> thy Wicked Book with <hi>Ham's Spirit,</hi> to the dishonour of God and grief of his good People, rendring them <hi>Apoſtates</hi> and <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vators,</hi> &amp;c. (belying them) and ſo telling and publiſhing thy ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders as in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askelon,</hi> to the gladding the hearts of the Uncircumciſed, and ſo manifeſting thy own ſhame in going about to ſlander ſuch as God hath Clothed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And my Book ſtands ſtill a Witneſs and a Teſtimony upon thy head, and thoſe that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged thee, againſt your foul Spirit.</p>
            <p>And is there none come off in <hi>Wilts</hi> and <hi>Briſtol,</hi> ſince the 20th of the Sixth Month 1675.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:172734:12"/>I ſay, is there none come off from <hi>J. Story, J. Wilkinſon,</hi> and <hi>W. Rogers?</hi> Yes ſurely, Let <hi>Wilts</hi> and <hi>Briſtol</hi> ſpeak whether none there have come off from them, and teſtified againſt their foul Spirit.</p>
            <p>And <hi>W. R.</hi> unjuſtly compares <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi> and his <hi>falſe Prophecy with</hi> Samuel <hi>the Prophet againſt Saul, which he thinks, ſhould be a Warning to</hi> G. F. <hi>and others to hearken to</hi> J. W<hi>'s falſe Prophecy:</hi> We have <hi>taken Warning</hi> but it is concerning thine, <hi>J. Story</hi>'s and <hi>J. W</hi>'s Spirit, and do <hi>warn</hi> others to reject his <hi>falſe Spirit</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy,</hi> which if we ſhould have believed, then we might have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of it as ſome have done.</p>
            <p>And ſo <hi>W. Rogers</hi>'s and <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi>'s own party is broken to pieces, as the <hi>Certificates</hi> aforeſaid manifeſt, and Gods People are ſetled and eſtabliſhed upon the Rock of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> and by the <hi>Certificate</hi> that followeth, you may Read <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi>'s Apoſtacy; how he kept not his firſt Habitation. And was not <hi>J. Story,</hi> and is not <hi>W. Rogers</hi> of the ſame Spirit with him.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="certificate">
               <body>
                  <head>A Certificate</head>
                  <p>FRom <hi>William Gandie</hi> in Relation of ſome words in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe between him and <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi> at <hi>William Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> houſe ſome Years Paſt, concerning the Perſecution that was made by the late Act againſt <hi>Conventicles,</hi> and how liable ſuch as I (to wit <hi>William Gandie</hi>) who had a meeting twice in the Week at my houſe, were liable to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, becauſe the Informers did know certainly where to find us, but ſaid <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi> to me, we have taken a Courſe in <hi>Weſtmorland,</hi> to prevent the informers for having their Prey upon us, for we appoint our Meetings in Private places as Gills and Cloughs, where we think they cannot find us— Then I asked <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi> how they did appoint their meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, whether Publickly, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>— And <hi>J. W.</hi> ſaid no, private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one to the other,—And then how ſuch Friends ſhould know, who might not be acquainted? or not be at the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172734:12"/>
And <hi>J. W.</hi> anſwered, they kept ſome one on a Hill, as a Boy, to give ſuch Friends Notice by ſignes, as by the Hat, or ſome ſuch like ſignes, whither they might repair to the Meeting—And further <hi>J. W.</hi> adviſed me, to put the Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at my houſe, to meet under a great Oake, that ſtands before my door in the <hi>Lane</hi> or <hi>Kings</hi> high way, which would prevent them of Twenty Pounds due for my fine, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is as near as I can remember the Words that paſſed betwixt us.</p>
                  <p>Now I have often heard that <hi>William Rogers</hi> was about to Print, but I hoped they would not have been ſo very Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, thus to ſhew their Enmity; but they will have their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</p>
                  <p>So in this Day we may Bleſs the Lord that we have heen preſerved from that Spirit in our Countie.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>William Gandie.</signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Cheſhire</hi> 
                        <date>the 9th of the 2d Month <hi>1681.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>W. R. ſays, Part 8. Pag 14. <hi>Not one Iota of an Order approved by</hi> G. F <hi>s Party can be Diſpenſed with to maintain the Ancient fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the People</hi> called Quakers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> But W. R. <hi>hath not ſhewed</hi> wherein, nor what all theſe Orders are, nor our Ancient fellowſhip: This is but his empty Clamour like the Reſt. And</p>
            <p>Part 8 Pag. 13. W. R. ſaith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>whether ſuch of</hi> G. F<hi>'s party, as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare Dis-union with another Perſon on the meer foot of that other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Conſcientious refuſal to propoſe the Intention of his</hi> Marriage <hi>to a Meeting of Women Diſtinct from Men, be not a Badge of</hi> Apoſtacy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> This <hi>W. R.</hi> would inſinuate, but hath proved nothing with his dark queries, nor named theſe other Perſons, who do Conſcentiouſly refuſe. And pag. 15. he ſpeaks of his Declarations of the Ancient Brethren, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> exalting Chriſt over all in <hi>Male</hi> and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172734:13"/>
               <hi>Female,</hi> the hope of Glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And why ſhould not Chriſt in the <hi>Female,</hi> as well as the <hi>Male;</hi> or why ſhould not faithful Women have a ſight into the Marriages in the Covenant of God? And how can any Perſon Conſcientiously refuſe or deny it.</p>
            <p>And is not <hi>W. R.</hi> ſo high and lofty, that <hi>he and his followers do ſcorn to lay a Marriage before Chriſt in the</hi> Female, <hi>as well as in the Male, or before the faithful Women as well as the men, though in their Meetings they may be Diſtinct or apart from the men, as abſent in the Body, preſent in the Spirit one with another.</hi> That ſo <hi>W. R.</hi> hath n t yet prov'd <hi>Seperation.</hi> For ſome of <hi>J. Wilkinſons</hi> Party have called the <hi>Womens-Meetings</hi> an <hi>Idol;</hi> I am a Witneſs of it.</p>
            <p>Part 6. Page 4. <hi>W. R.</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Oppoſers Recriminating Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith, <hi>it hath been one motive among others Occaſioning me once more to appear in Print: and one part of my End therein is, that ſome ſhort Diſcovery may be made of the ways and means, by which ſome ſimple-minded have heen betrayed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And he further ſpeaking of the <hi>Second Days Meeting in London,</hi> ſaith, <hi>Theſe few Lines ſhall remain on Record to the Infamy and ſhame of ſuch as have approved the aforeſaid Books or Papers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſwer, W. R. <hi>This ſhame and infamy</hi> will <hi>remain upon Record</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ſelf and thine Adherents. And muſt not theſe thou calls <hi>ſimple, inſnared, betrayed Friends, pin their faith on thy ſleeve to unbetray them?</hi> But who the <hi>ſimple betrayed Friends are, what they are betray'd in, and what our Recriminating Reflections</hi> are, thou haſt not here named. And,</p>
            <p>W. R. Thou ſayſt, Part 8 Page 11. <hi>The ſenſe I have of the ſnare at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending many through Conformity to other mens Lines made ready to their hands in blind Obedience,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſwers.</hi> But who are thoſe that are Conformable to other Mens Lines made ready to their hands, and where are the Lines they are Comformable unto? Why haſt thou not Printed them all? or muſt I pin my faith on thy ſleeve in this alſo? But what! <hi>W. R.</hi> who <hi>appeareſt in Print, for the ſimple and betrayed,</hi> is not the <hi>Grace of God</hi> within, and the Light of Chriſt ſufficient, <hi>by which all muſt</hi> be kept to their own, to ſee Chriſt their Saviour, that they need not look at thy <hi>Lines made ready to their hands;</hi> which inſtead of <hi>unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving</hi> them, will <hi>deceive</hi> them the more.</p>
            <p>And as for the <hi>Second Days Meetings</hi> all thy <hi>brawlings</hi> and <hi>Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:172734:13"/>
againſt the Friends Concern'd in that Meeting, they in the Lords Power do not regard, as knowing thy words to be of no Credit with them that fear the Lord.</p>
            <p>And <hi>W. R.</hi> are not all the Books, that thou haſt Printed againſt the Faithful (in which thou haſt ſhot all thy <hi>Wicked Darts</hi> with thy foul Language) like unto <hi>J. Story</hi> and <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi>'s <hi>Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> thou drew up for them, which thou calledſt a Rattle <hi>to pleaſe Children?</hi> And could there have been more <hi>Wickedneſs</hi> known in Man and <hi>Diſſimulation,</hi> than that way? For was not thy Intent thereby to <hi>deceive?</hi> And was not that a mark and a Badge of thy great <hi>Apoſtacy from the Light of Chriſt and his Truth?</hi> But the Children of the Light, neither thou, nor <hi>J. Story,</hi> nor <hi>J. Wilkinſon,</hi> were able to <hi>deceive;</hi> And therefore thou Roareſt now like a <hi>Bull in a Nett,</hi> and reproacheſt ſuch Faithful Friends, as here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired thy Eternal Good.</p>
            <p>And all thy Printed Books are like unto the <hi>Rattle</hi> thou ſpeakſt of <hi>to pleaſe Children</hi> (and they muſt be <hi>Children</hi> indeed, and <hi>ſimple,</hi> and <hi>Betrayed</hi> from Chriſt and his Light, that believe thy <hi>Rattles.</hi> But all that walk in the Light, and are grafted into Chriſt, ſee over thee and them, and thou canſt not deceive them. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou art in ſuch a Toſs and Tempeſt, and in a fretful, Reſtleſs Spirit.</p>
            <p>And what <hi>W. R!</hi> Wouldeſt thou have a Meeting to wait upon the Lord to Manifeſt thy <hi>Words, Works</hi> and <hi>Spirit?</hi> The Lord hath ſufficiently diſcovered both thy <hi>Words, Works</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> by his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Power and Spirit, and judged them. Thou ſayſt, <hi>Thou art for Peace;</hi> Then call in all thy <hi>Dirty Wicked Books,</hi> and Condemn them. And do not oppoſe the <hi>Light</hi> of Chriſt and his <hi>Grace,</hi> the <hi>Truth</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> in his people, nor the Goſpel, the power of God in Men and Women, which hath led them to Chriſt and God, to meet in his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> by which they are gathered to him, to take care of Gods Truth (which is their Duty) that he be not dishonoured, and the Camp of God may be kept Clean; And to ſee that all <hi>Marriages</hi> may be performed deſently and in Order, that Chriſt in the <hi>Female,</hi> as well as in the <hi>Male</hi> may have an <hi>Eye</hi> in them, that both <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female</hi> being Faithful to God may be <hi>Meet-helps</hi> together in Truth and in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs in Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:172734:14"/>But if thou doſt proceed, and goeſt on, <hi>Gods Eternal Sword of his Spirit is drawn againſt thee and that Spirit that takes thy part;</hi> and therefore be warned. For its Judgment is begun, and his <hi>Sword</hi> will not be <hi>put up,</hi> untill it hath perfected its Work: And when thou feeleſt it <hi>cut,</hi> and the <hi>Terrors</hi> of the <hi>Lord upon thee,</hi> for thy Wicked Works ſake; in which thou haſt cryed Peace, Peace, but inſtead of <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> nothing <hi>but Deſtruction</hi> will come up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>William,</hi> O the Horror! when the <hi>Vengeance</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee for abuſing people with thy <hi>deceitful Rattles.</hi> Then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the <hi>tender Bowels</hi> of them, that ſought thy Eternal Good, and would have reclaimed thee; for hadſt thou kept to the Witneſs of God, and Judged <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> thou hadſt never followed this <hi>Diſorderly Spirit</hi> of the <hi>ſon</hi> of <hi>Perdition, which is exalted above all that is called God</hi> in thee, which ſeeks to betray Gods people and his Truth (<hi>Judas</hi> like) to the World.</p>
            <p>But if ever God ſhould be ſo Merciful to thee as to bring thee down to his Witneſs in thy ſelf, thou wouldeſt Lament the Day that ever thou eſpouſedſt that Spirit, that led <hi>J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> from the Truth, and ſo turned againſt the Faithful Friends and Children of the Light.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> Thou goeſt over and over in thy Books with ſlighting Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions againſt our Church-Government, and that in a lofty ſcoffing deſpiſing way: But I muſt tell thee, Chriſt who is the Governour hath eſtabliſhed by his Light, Power and Spirit, his Government in the hearts of all his Children of Light, who are li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Members of his Body, his Church, which he is the living head of; and the Gates of Hell ſhall not Prevaile againſt it. And by Chriſts Light in themſelves every <hi>Male</hi> and <hi>Female</hi> in the Church ſees their ſervice and their Duty to God.</p>
            <p>And <hi>W. R.</hi> Thou art buſying and mudling thy head about <hi>G. F</hi>'s Trade, thou hadſt better let <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Trade alone, who never did Diſpiſe the ſmalleſt honeſt calling upon Earth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> ſays Part 8. pag. 8. Let <hi>G. F.</hi> know whether he can receive it or no, that probable the Name of a Quaker might not have been deſpiſed ſo much by many as it now is, had he but followed the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>W. D.</hi> and other his fellowlabourers, keeping at ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt outward calling, inſtead of mudling his head to bring about a
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172734:14"/>
Conformity to his outward Orders. For I am fully ſatisfied in my Conſcience, that that noiſom ſcent that hath riſen like ſmoak from the bottomleſs Pit, hath been occaſioned from an Antichriſtian Promotion of his outward Orders; ſo far <hi>W. Rogers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now the Reader may ſee this Mans Spirit, he hath not given a Catalogue of theſe outward Orders, that the Reader may ſee them. And his Clamorous Tongue is but from his Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Spirit and Evil Conſcience, and the noiſom ſmoak of his bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſs Pit; but he cannot darken Gods Air; for the Sun of Righteouſneſs is ariſen with healing in his Wings, which ſhines over all; but God will judge him for his foul Language, and hard ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; for many weapons have been formed againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> ſince he was about 19 years old, and moved of the Lord to forſake all, and to follow the Lamb.</p>
            <p>But how can <hi>W. R.</hi> tell and be ſo confident that <hi>G. F.</hi> hath not ſome concerns in the outward Creation, having a Family? He hath not proved the Contrary, which he muſt do, or elſe ſtop his Mouth for ſhame; for if he had not, how is it, that he hath been under ſufferings and exerciſes ſome Years in ſeveral Courts for not paying Tithes, and his quoting <hi>W. D.</hi> in the caſe, is meer flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</p>
            <p>But what outward calling was that <hi>J. Story</hi> followed, and <hi>J. Wilkinſon,</hi> (when they were at <hi>Briſtol?</hi> let Friends of <hi>Briſtol</hi> and <hi>Wiltſhire</hi> ſpeak, where they were, and what it was,) whom he calls his honourable Brethren! and how have they kept the Name of a Quaker from being deſpiſed there! What a malitious Spirit guides thee to defame (if poſſible) <hi>G. F.</hi> that dear and faithful Servant of God, who through his Grace hath been ſuch a Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Inſtrument in his hand, that by him thouſands have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to God through the Goſpel committed to him, and have been <hi>ſhod</hi> with the preparation of it to <hi>defend</hi> them from the <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars</hi> and <hi>Thorns,</hi> the Exerciſes and Troubles of this evil World, to bring them to Peace with the Lord. And the Authority of God is with him ſtill to preſerve him to ſtand over the <hi>Devil,</hi> and thy <hi>foul Spirit,</hi> and all the <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Inſtruments of Iniquity;</hi> whoſe <hi>Life</hi> hath been preſerved through great ſufferings. And thoſe wicked <hi>Darts,</hi> which have been <hi>ſhot</hi> at him by thee and ſuch <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates</hi> and <hi>Envious ones</hi> as thou art, have <hi>recoiled back again</hi> into
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172734:15"/>
their own evil Souls. And who yet ever hated him and ſcorned him as thou doſt, that ever proſpered as to Godward, but in the end <hi>periſhed</hi> and <hi>withered?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>W. R.</hi> thy <hi>diſdain</hi> and <hi>folly</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> appears in Reflecting about <hi>G. F.</hi> his <hi>following no outward Calling,</hi> who is in his <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Service</hi> exerciſed with all his might, that in the end he may give up a bleſſed and faithful account through the Eternal <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Ever-living God of his <hi>Calling</hi> and <hi>Service,</hi> he was in his young years called unto, forſaking all other <hi>Callings</hi> and <hi>Concerns</hi> in this World to do the Work he was <hi>called</hi> unto; and is ſtill in his <hi>Calling;</hi> and who in this our day hath <hi>travelled, laboured</hi> and <hi>ſuffered</hi> more on <hi>Truth</hi>'s Account, than he hath done? Who is ſtill <hi>ſpending</hi> himſelf, that in the end he may be ſpent in the Work of it, and lay down his head in Peace and Joy in the Lord. And I am ſenſible, that all the Witneſſes of God in his Tabernacle will ariſe to judge and witneſs againſt thee and thine Abettors in that <hi>foul Spirit,</hi> by which you are acted to Blaſpheme God, his Truth and faithful people. And now if <hi>W. R.</hi> by outward Orders, means the Men and Womens Meetings, which <hi>G. F.</hi> and many other faithful Brethren and Elders in Chriſt, were moved in the Power and Spirit of the Lord to direct people to ſet up ſuch Meetings, did and do anſwer the Spirit of God, in all that fear him; and with the Spirit of God we witneſs the Authority of them to be the Power of God; And we do witneſs with the Spirit of God a great ſervice in them and for them to ſee and take care for the Poor, and for the Widdows and Fatherleſs; and to exhort and admoniſh ſuch that walk not according to the Goſpel of Chriſt Jeſus, or cauſe his Name to be diſhonoured or blaſphemed. And to ſee that all that do Marry, have their Relations Conſent, and be free from Intanglements with all other Perſons in Relation to Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age; and to ſee, that the Widdow and Fatherleſs, be not wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their Eſtates in Marriage. And we do not limit the Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Women in Jeſus Chriſt from their exerciſe and care in ſuch things, but that all things may be ſeen to be done in Truth and Righteouſneſs, to the Praiſe and Glory of God. And theſe be the outward Orders <hi>W. R.</hi> ſpeaks of, that ſtink, and are ſo noiſom, like the ſmoak from the bottomleſs Pit, and from an Antichriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion in <hi>W. R</hi>'s Eyes and Noſe; I tell him, we will ſtand by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172734:15"/>
them in Gods Power and Spirit againſt his wicked ſpirit; and God will Judge him for his foul and wicked words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> Thou ſaieſt, part 6. p. 5. 22. what is frequently brought to thy Ears, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thou ſaieſt witneſs the Perſecution raiſed againſt <hi>J. S.</hi> &amp; <hi>J. W.</hi> and proceeding againſt <hi>John Ainloe</hi> at a Quarterly Meeting in the Iſle of <hi>Ely.</hi> And I really pitty <hi>J. A.</hi> that he ſhould ever have given the leaſt occaſion wherefore ſuch a wicked ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary as thou art ſhould be an advocate for him againſt us. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Poor <hi>J. A!</hi> once Dear to me; my Soul wiſhes thee well.</p>
            <p>But why did not <hi>W. R.</hi> ſet down the matter of Fact, that the Quarterly meeting had againſt <hi>John Ainloe,</hi> together with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers Names, that brought theſe things to his Ears, and not to hide them under his dark Curtain? But has <hi>W. R.</hi> ſent his informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the ſaid Quarterly meeting, that the informers have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, that he might know the Truth of it, before he publiſht it to the Nations in Print? But we can expect little otherwiſe but General Clamours from this Spirit.</p>
            <p>And it is a groſs abuſe, and ſlender to ſay that ever Perſecution was raiſed againſt <hi>J. W.</hi> &amp; <hi>J. S.</hi> by the Children of Light, but they ſought their good; who willfully reſiſted all tender Admonitions. And though with thy Wicked Spirit thou over and over ſmiteſt at <hi>G. F.</hi> and other Faithful Elders; yet both he and many others can ſay, Many Weapons have been formed againſt him and us, by Apoſtates and prophane: But the Lord ſaith, no Weapon that is formed againſt thee ſhall proſper; and every Tongue that ſhall riſe up in Judgment againſt thee, thou ſhalt condemn. This is the Heritage of the Servants of the Lord, and their Righteouſneſs is of me, ſaith the Lord: ſo God has Reſtrained the Weapons, and he gives Spirit and Power to Condemn thoſe Evil tongues, as thine, that riſe up in Judgment againſt them.</p>
            <p>And ſomething I have to ſay concerning that Scripture thou bringeſt <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. further to manifeſt thy folly, 6 part, p. 5. <hi>W. R.</hi> thou ſaieſt, if the meer Diſcovering of Nakedneſs by ſome profeſſor of Truth againſt another be a Sin, then doubtleſs <hi>Paul</hi> was a ſort of ſinner in leaving it on Record, that he withſtood <hi>Peter</hi> to the face, becauſe he was to be blamed for his Diſſimulation, read 2d. Chap. of the <hi>Gal.</hi> To this I anſwer that from the 14. verſe of the ſaid Chapter we learn, that <hi>Pauls</hi> reproof was before all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172734:16"/>
Men, <hi>&amp;c. Anſw.</hi> This proof <hi>W. R</hi> brings to cover himſelf in Printing of his book, and to abuſe the faithful; And this proof he brings for a looking-glaſs for <hi>G. F.</hi> to behold his face in, as he ſcornfully ſays. And now reader trie his Doctrine, whether it be not a proper Looking-glaſs for himſelf, and his Company. For 1ſt. did <hi>Paul</hi> publiſh what he blamed <hi>Peter</hi> for, and withſtood him in? and did he ſpread it up and down in the Nations, yea and beyond the ſeas, as <hi>W. R.</hi> or ſome of his Abettors have done? and have not ſome Prieſts and profeſſors got them, that are Enemies to the Light of Chriſt? let <hi>W. R.</hi> prove, that <hi>Paul</hi> did publiſh a book againſt <hi>Peter,</hi> as he hath done againſt Friends; and <hi>Pauls</hi> leaving it upon Record, was in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> and was not that the Church of Chriſt there? And therefore I put <hi>W. R.</hi> to prove it, that <hi>Paul</hi> did publiſh and ſpread his book among the unbelieving Jews, or Gentile-<hi>Galatians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now we muſt trie <hi>W. R.</hi> with the Scripture he brings, that the Reader may ſee how he hath abuſed the Scripture.</p>
            <p>For in the 2d. Chapter to the <hi>Gal.</hi> verſ. 14. to this he ſaith, that from the 14. verſe of that Chapter we may learn that <hi>Pauls</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof was before all men. But let <hi>W. R.</hi> take his Looking-glaſs, and ſee whether he learns any ſuch thing, in the 2d. Chap. to the <hi>Gal.</hi> verſ. the 14.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles words are theſe; But when I ſaw, that they walked not uprightly according to the Truth of the Goſpel, I ſaid unto <hi>Peter,</hi> before them all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now <hi>before them all,</hi> who were <hi>them all?</hi> were they all the believers then preſent? he doth not mention here (all men) but ſays, before them all, who were them all? were they not them that were preſent? for here is not the Word, <hi>Men</hi> in this verſe; and the Reader may ſee that <hi>W. R</hi> has ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly wronged, and falſifyed the Scripture here.</p>
            <p>And <hi>W. R.</hi> goes about to confirm it, and ſaith, If any ſay <hi>Paul</hi> did not Publiſh it in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askalon;</hi> To this He ſaith, I Anſwer that from the 14th verſe of the 2d chap. to the <hi>Gal.</hi> we learn, that <hi>Paul</hi>'s Reproof was before all Men. But <hi>W. R.</hi> and his <hi>we,</hi> have not learn't this from that Scripture, neither did <hi>W. R.</hi> learn there, that he ſhould Publiſh his Book in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askalon,</hi> neither that <hi>Paul</hi> Publiſht that which he blamed <hi>Peter</hi> for in <hi>Gath</hi> and <hi>Askalon;</hi> which thou Fallaciouſly bringeſt to cover thy Spirit, but inſtead
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:172734:16"/>
of covering thy ſelf, thou haſt tumbled thy ſelf over and over in the Dirt, and ſhewed thy own Nakedneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>W. R.</hi> ſays, Part 6. pag. 5. Tis frequently brought to my Ears, that our Oppoſers common diſcourſe is, that I have written a wicked Book againſt the faithful Friends of Truth; that if all I had therein written were true, yet the Spirit that gave it forth muſt be wrong, and the ſame with <hi>Hams,</hi> becauſe it diſcovers the Nakedneſs of a Father.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But if therein he alludes to the 5th Page of my Book, he perverts my Words, and the Intent of them; for I do not ſay, it diſcovers the Nakedneſs of a Father, as he hath Mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly Writ; but my Words are theſe, That <hi>W. R.</hi> hath endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to uncover the Nakedneſs of ſuch as once he accounted his Brethren and Elders, or Fathers, whom God hath cloathed. For thou haſt not, neither canſt thou uncover the Nakedneſs of ſuch Brethren, and Elders or Fathers, to preſent them Naked to the View of the whole World, by Publiſhing of thy Book ſo that herein thou haſt really done worſe then <hi>Ham,</hi> for he wickedly and really uncovered his Fathers Nakedneſs; but thou wickedly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoureſt to do it, or ſo to preſent it to the View of the World, to make the Uncircumciſed rejoyce; ſo that thy Sin herein is doubled; for thou haſt repreſented the thing which really is not ſo in it ſelf, that is, they are not Naked, but Cloathed with Gods Righteouſneſs, whom thou haſt repreſented to be Naked; but haſt diſcovered thy own Nakedneſs, and herein thou haſt exceeded <hi>Ham,</hi> who diſcovered a real Nakedneſs. And alſo thy malice and wickedneſs in it hath exceeded his, whoſe work as I ſaid in mine, may be ſaid to have been a haſty raſh Action, done on a ſudden, without premeditation; but thou haſt long premeditated, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured to bring forth thy wicked Book in Print, and endeavoureſt to betray and deceive Peoples minds, that they may believe thy Lies, Juggling and Legerdemain, in this matter</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Chriſtopher Tayler</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:172734:17"/>
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>SInce theſe Sheets were written, I have ſeen three Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sheets from one <hi>Thomas Criſp,</hi> a man outwardly unknown to me, but that he is of an evil Spirit I know well, and as I am credibly Informed, he is one of the old Apoſtate Quakers, that went out from Truth many Years ſince; for they ſay he was once convinced of it, but never ſince had the happineſs, becauſe of his evil heart, to return into it again, as I am informed, but went on ſtill backwards more and more, and was Married by a Prieſt, and pleads for Gods allowance to him in ſo doing by his Spirit, and alſo pleads for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of paying Tythes by the allowance of Gods Spirit, and alſo for the uſe of the Language Truth diſowns, as in the ſecond Part of <hi>Babels</hi> Builders, p. 5. and in all this would cover himſelf under the Notion and Profeſſion of one of his Brother <hi>William Rogers</hi> his Chriſtian Quakers; Now let the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Reader conſider, whether thoſe aforementioned were the Principles of our Ancient Friends and Brethren, who came forth in the beginning in the great Authority and Power of God; and doth not this envious Spirited man, appear ſtill to be in his Apoſtacy from the Truth? doth not his Language and Principles bewray him, to be no friend to the truly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Quaker? And it may be he thinks now he hath a grand opportunity, by his joyning with his Brethren, <hi>W. R. J. Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyman,</hi> &amp;c. in their Rebellion and gainſaying the Truth, to become a kind of dark ſect-maſter, amongſt their (ſo call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) Chriſtian Quakers; but they are blind indeed; who cannot ſee ſuch an Idle-headed Apoſtate as this man is, who would draw Diſciples after him, by reproaching Gods Truth and People.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:172734:17"/>His three Sheets are by him called [the ſecond and third Part of <hi>Babels</hi> Builders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] wherein his Idle brain hath been at work, and he hath uſed my name, or the Letters of it eight or nine times over; And his Text againſt me it ſeems is out of the 3d page of my Epiſtle of Caution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where ſpeaking of dear <hi>G. F.</hi> abuſed by <hi>W. R.</hi> I affirm that ſtill he is made Inſtrumental in the hand of the Lord to bring forth bleſſed things for the ſervice of God, and his Truth, from the Oracles of the Divine Breath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This <hi>T. C.</hi> cannot endure to hear of, no more than his Brother <hi>W. R.</hi> becauſe they would have him and thouſands more that fear the Lord to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Apoſtates, and ſo render them dead, and their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine breath ſtopt, and ſo altogether uncapable to bring forth bleſſed things for the Service of God and his Truth; but that is certainly their own Condition, ſpeaking perverſe things in a heady, wilful mind, againſt ſuch as through the Grace of God have kept the true faith of Gods Elect, who cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by their ſpeaking perverſe things againſt us, but now Reader obſerve his forgery, in his 2d page, ſpeaking of our Idol <hi>G. F.</hi> his Laws, and would inſinuate thoſe he calls <hi>G. F.</hi> his Laws to be an Idol, and me to be an Idolator to Adore them as from the Oracles of the Divine breath, and in the 4th page, he ſpeaks of my having given <hi>G. F.</hi> unfitting titles, and names, but tells not what they are; and in the 12th page, he is highly offended that I ſhould affirm that <hi>G. F.</hi> &amp;c. are the beſt among the Quakers, or the beſt of Gods ſervants; ſee his baſe fooliſh Spirit: what has this <hi>T. C. W. R. J. P.</hi> &amp;c. done in their time for God in his ſervice? have they ever been Inſtrumental to turn one perſon to Righteouſneſs, ſince they were called Quakers? or when did any of them Print any thing for God, before they begun to puſh with their horns againſt us; Now they are become Champions, ſuch as they are, to draw from the Truth into their own Condition who are
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172734:18"/>
Apoſtatiz'd from it as much as in them lies, and ſo are the Miniſters of the Devil and Antichriſt, like ravening even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wolves and Bears they wait to meet with their Prey, and devour the Righteous ſeed, but God will confound them, and their wicked deſign, and we trample in the power of God upon their evil Spirit, if they do their worſt. And as Chriſt Jeſus ſaid to Judas, that Traytor, That thou doſt, do quickly; ſo that they do, let them do quickly, that when they have done their wicked work without repentance they may go to their proper place.— And as for my adoreing <hi>G. F.</hi> and his Laws, it is an ignorant, ſottiſh, Idle, Childiſh Story; I knew before thou <hi>T. C. W. R.</hi> I Pennyman, were called Quakers how to Adore and Worſhip the true and living God, and ſtil do know how to love and dearly to eſteem ſuch Ancient Elders and Friends as were and are ſtill Inſtrumental to bring forth bleſſed things for the ſervice of God and his Truth; and this is done by a Divine breath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and thus to affirm is neither to Adore or Worſhip Men or Things, but to Aſſert the Truth, which thou haſt not diſproved with thy ſcandalous lying breath, and thy lyes and ſlanders are detected, and I charged thee to make thy charge good wherein I am ſuch an one as Adore <hi>G. F.</hi> and his laws, as thou calls them; bring thy proof, or eat thy words; for thou haſt groſsly perverted mine, as the Reader may ſee; and the leaſt thing thats done by the weakeſt Inſtrument in obedience to God's Will, is by a Divine Spirit or Breath, which thou ſcoffs at, and falſely calleſt it, Adoring or worſhiping <hi>G. F,</hi> and his laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and I lay it upon thee when thou Prints again, to ſet down this Idol what it is, and ſuch as thou calls <hi>G. F,</hi> his laws, ſet down a Catalogue of them all, for peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will not elſe I hope be ſatisfied to pin their Faith on thy, or thy brethrens ſleeves, to believe your bawlings againſt them, as if they were ſome miſhapen Monſtrous things, Now <hi>T. Criſp,</hi> I muſt tell thee, thy cauſe is naught, and thy bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172734:18"/>
alſo, and thy and your Battle of Wickedneſs will come to an end, and I pray God preſerve his People unto himſelf from your muttering, peeping Counſels, who lye in wait to deſtroy the ſimple-minded with your Craft and Wickedneſs; and this is my Teſtimony, that your Work is wicked, and the God of Heaven is highly diſpleaſed with you; and if I ſhould never more in my native Country appear in Print, or however I may in this outwatd World be diſpoſed on, I ſay, I affirm in the preſence of God, that thou <hi>T. C. W. R. J. Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyman,</hi> and all the reſt, who in their hearts and ſouls have reſolutely Eſpouſed your Cauſe againſt <hi>G. F.</hi> and thouſands others, both Elders and Friends of Truth, that though for a while, the Lord may ſuffer you as an exerciſe and tryal to his People, yet your wicked Rebellion and gainſaying will come to an end; and except it be poſſible you can find a place of Repentance, your end will be miſerable; and this Teſtimony I leave behind me, however the merciful, good and moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God may diſpoſe of me. Oh! my native Country, how dear is my love to thee! Praying that the Lords holy Truth may ſtill prevail in thee, and that my Friends and Brethren in the Truth may be kept faithful in it, that his Glory may ſtill ariſe, and his Power prevail, ſo that this Nation may be as a Nurſery to the Nations about it, to ſend forth Rigbteous and Faithful Plants with ſucceſs into his Vineyard, that thouſands and ten thouſands may be alarm'd by the ſound of Truth, to come out of their Graves of ſin and unbelief, to the Reſurrection, and Salvation of Jeſus Chriſt, Amen.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="affidavit">
               <body>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:172734:19"/>
                  <head>The 8th of the 9th Month, 1681.</head>
                  <p>Thomas Criſp <hi>ſaid,</hi> That he hath paid <hi>Tithes</hi> lately; and that the Spirit of God did or might allow him to pay <hi>Tithes</hi> or <hi>Marry</hi> by a <hi>Prieſt;</hi> And that by the ſame Spirit of God another might be required not to pay them, or not to do the ſame things.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This</hi> Thomas Criſp <hi>ſpoke the day and Year aboveſaid, and conſented to have it Writ and Printed; and took a Copy of the aforeſaid Words.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Witneſs</hi> John Field, Jun.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>See what an <hi>Agent W. R. J. Story</hi> and <hi>J. Wilkinſon</hi> have gotten, who is a falſe, wicked perverter of the Truth and of Friends Ancient Teſtimonies in the Truth in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. Oh monſtruos! To ſet the Spirit of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God againſt it ſelf! Did we ever thirty years ſince, and ſince to this day, Preach for Doctrine, and tell Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>The Spirit of God did or might allow them to pay Tithes or Marry by a Prieſt; and that by the ſame Spirit of God another might be required not to pay them, or not to do the ſame things?</hi> Here the <hi>Reader</hi> may ſee their Confuſion and Blaſphemy againſt <hi>Gods Spirit</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> what they
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172734:19"/>
would be at under the Pretence of <hi>Liberty:</hi> ſo that at the laſt (for ought I know) they may commit groſs <hi>Evils,</hi> which Truth Condemns, and ſay, It is their <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>God allows them to do it by his Spirit, though others may be Judged for it;</hi> And ſo by this wicked principle uſher in all manner of <hi>Ranteriſm.</hi> Alas! how miſerably blind are thoſe that cannot diſcern theſe mens wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly deſign, how mad and wicked they are to make void the <hi>Croſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and wreſt the Truth to ſerve the Turn of their own <hi>Licentious Spirits</hi> and <hi>Carnal Minds.</hi> And I doubt not but ſome of theſe <hi>Brawlers</hi> againſt us, are got too far with their <hi>Liberty</hi> into the <hi>Ditch</hi> already to their own deſtruction, who do not deſerve the name of a <hi>Quaker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now at this time, when we are expos'd to great ſufferings by <hi>Impriſonments, ſpoiling of Goods,</hi> &amp;c. for theſe Apoſtates <hi>T. C. W. R.</hi> and their Adherents to be ſo malitious, as at ſuch a time as this, to render us <hi>Odious</hi> to the World by ſpreading and Printing their defaming, lying, and ſlanderous Books againſt us: All ſober <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> may ſee, how the <hi>malitious mask</hi> is taken off theſe <hi>Babel-builders,</hi> and ſo their Spirit is ſeen to be the ſame with thoſe old <hi>Apoſtates,</hi> that are gone before them; And that they do but hypocritically deceive People in preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding themſelves to be <hi>Quakers,</hi> who are none, nor <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> of the <hi>Light,</hi> as may be ſeen by their Books and Principles; And from that meek Spirit of Life and Truth they are gone; and under pretence of exalting Chriſt and his Kingdom, they are <hi>exalting ſelf,</hi> and with it are oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Order of the Goſpel, and the Law of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Life,</hi> which is in Chriſt Jeſus: and their <hi>wicked Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> and <hi>Work</hi> is to be Judged out of the <hi>Camp</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:172734:20"/>
               <hi>John Story</hi> being asked, <hi>why he did not hinder</hi> William Rogers <hi>from Printing his great wicked Book againſt us?</hi> in my hearing he Anſwered, <hi>That William Rogers was ſuch a Strong Willful Man that if he ſet upon a thing, he would do it, if all the World ſet againſt him.</hi> So that <hi>W. R.</hi> may ſee what <hi>Eſteem <hi>J. S.</hi>
               </hi> (his great <hi>Elder</hi> and <hi>Brother</hi>) had of him, if he ſpake not in Hypocricy at that time.</p>
            <p>And <hi>W. R.</hi> what is that Honour that thou ſo often over and over in thy great wicked Book giveth and applaudeth to <hi>J. Story,</hi> and <hi>J. Wilkinſon?</hi> is it from Above or from Below, Spiritual or Temporal, Heavenly or Earthly? Anſwer <hi>Yea</hi> or <hi>Nay.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:172734:20"/>
            <head>Againſt <hi>W. R's</hi> Charge of Popery, and others.</head>
            <p>WHereas <hi>W. R.</hi> 8th Part Pag. 3. as in many other places, Chargeth us with Popiſh Principles and Practices. And Page 5. reflects on learning from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors. And in particular <hi>R. Baxter,</hi> as if <hi>G. F</hi>'s Cauſe were at a low Ebb, in being beholding to him and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians. To theſe few words at preſent. <hi>G. F</hi>'s Cauſe is no more beholding to him and Presbyterians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than to <hi>W. R. J. S.</hi> and <hi>J. W.</hi> &amp;c. when they confeſs to Truth againſt themſelves, or practiſe it, and yet blame it in others. To that purpoſe I cite <hi>R. B.</hi> and others,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>C.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 45.</note> who in his Hiſtory of Biſhops and Councils, ſpeaking of ſome Papiſts, ſays, he cannot believe they were ill men; wherein I compare his Charity (though accounted of the riged Sect) with <hi>W. R</hi>'s, though owning Univerſal Grace, yet excluding <hi>Micha</hi>'s Mother from his, and though the Presbyterians now joyn with <hi>W. R</hi>'s abettors, againſt Womens Services in the Church, yet formerly they did not ſo; But ſtood for them, as ſome alſo of other Perſwaſions. As D. <hi>M. Sutcliff</hi> Dean of <hi>Chelſy</hi> Colledge,<note place="margin">Falſe ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blant, &amp;c. c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> a Cheiftain for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> proves from a Sermon of theirs on <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.8. ſaying, unleſs they have Deaconeſſes, they exclaim that the Church is maimed, (and condemn all other Churches) becauſe Widows are Members of the Church, as a Body, ſhewing mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the ſaid Doctor confeſſes, that Ancient Churches, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them, had Widows and Virgins, but not as Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers (which Titles we ſtand not for,<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid. cap. <hi>13.</hi> from Act. <hi>13.1.</hi> Cap. maſſ. Muſculus Soc. Com. Of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of the Church lib. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> nor ſingle life, nor other circumſtances, which vary with times, but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) And ſays, if ſuch were reſtored, they would reſemble Nuns. But <hi>Junius</hi> a great light in the Proteſtant-Church, as ſome call him, in the place cited already, ſpeaking of Deaconeſſes, ſays, they did partake
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172734:21"/>
of the Miniſtry or Deaconry, as far as Women were fitter for it. And that ſome footſteps of this remains in Hoſpitalls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where Nunes ſometimes are placed for ſervice, as Rubbiſh of a decayed houſe. And wiſhes that the Miniſtry of Women were reſtored, according to the Rule of God's Word, the Examples of the Ancients, and the Lawes of Charity. This to ſtop the ſcorn and aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that I read in Popiſh Authors.<note place="margin">Cave, Gualter, Bucan.</note> For beſides <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>'s Abridgment, a Proteſtant, I name three other Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants beſides theſe here; And could do many beſides in time, I Queſtion not <hi>Henoch Clapham,</hi> who writes alſo againſt the Puritans (as <hi>Sutcliff,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clapham Brief of Bible, <hi>2.</hi> Part. Staff. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> ſome whereof were for Deaconeſſes; as appears in his Epiſtle Dedicatory to the Arch Biſhop, in K. <hi>James</hi>'s Reign, yet confeſſeth that almoſt all grant eaſily that there were two ſorts of Deacons, or Church-ſervitors, the firſt of men <hi>Act.</hi> 6, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8. the ſecond of Women, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.9, <hi>&amp;c. Rom.</hi> 16.1. And that they attended the ſick and impotent many held. So hee. But ſome as the Prieſts cry Popery, Popery, as Papiſts cried Hereſy, Hereſy, to people Ignorant of thoſe things; without any proof? but as Thieves in the head of the Hue-and-cry; by their ſuſpitious clamours to cauſe the honeſt man to be taken that they may eſcape. As may be ſeen in a piece with <hi>G. W.</hi> I have writ in anſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer to a Prieſt about <hi>Durham,</hi> about Juſtification. And in an anſwer to a Prieſt in <hi>Scotland</hi> by <hi>Geo. Keith,</hi> called, <hi>Quakeriſm no Popery.</hi> And now ſeeing theſe men cry Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, but prove it not, I ſhall in ſhort at preſent prove our Aſſertions not Popery from the Chieftains againſt Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Controv.</hi> 4. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> D. <hi>Whitaker,</hi> and <hi>Juell</hi> againſt <hi>Bellarmin</hi> and <hi>Stapleton,</hi> the Great Popiſh Polemic Doctors. The firſt <hi>Whitaker,</hi> ſays, not only <hi>Peter,</hi> but any the meaneſt Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter can impoſe and bind the Conſciences of men, not as Author,<note place="margin">Explic. Cat. de peccat. Act. diſt. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> but as Miniſter; but I find not in him, or any other, the Condition if they be convinced. Nay, on the contrary, I find in <hi>Urſin</hi> aſſented to by <hi>Panaeus</hi> and <hi>Junius,</hi> all eminent Proteſtants, a diſtinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſin againſt Conſcience, and ſin not againſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:172734:21"/>
grounded on 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. with whom <hi>Beza</hi> agrees;<note place="margin">Beza on the place. In Oben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heim pugn. Expoſ. pag. <hi>607.</hi>
               </note> that Ignorance is a ſin, though not ſo great. The like with <hi>Brentius</hi> an Eminent Proteſtant alſo, and <hi>Theophylact,</hi> called a Father, on <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.41. and ch. 15.22. <hi>Juel, Act.</hi> 27. againſt D. <hi>Cole,</hi> affirming ignorance to be the Mother of Devotion, cites <hi>Aguſtin</hi> on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33. ſaying, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Ignorance is the Kingdom of Error, <hi>Origen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Origen on numb. hom. <hi>27.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Conc. Tolet <hi>4.</hi> can. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> that the Devils have poſſeſſion of them that are Ignorant. <hi>Toletan</hi> Council, that Ignorance is the mother of all Error. But the Libertin Doctrine is, If Ignorant of, or not ſeeing it our Duty, that is free from Conviction, then free from Error, free from ſin, free from Satan, free from Church cenſure, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And then is not Ignorance the mother of Freedom from ſin and Satan. And how comes that ſhort of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, That its the mother of Piety, as they ſay, This is the Conſequence, that Ignorance is a ſafe State, though Chriſt ſayes, the blind may be led into the Ditch. I know of none that ſay among us, follow us blindly without any ſight at all. But to keep the ſingle eye open, to ſee in meaſure, to ſee whom to follow, as they follow Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.19.</note> For if they abide in darkneſs, loving darkneſs rather than light, and hating it by which they ſhould ſee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.2.</note> 'tis through their evil deeds: And if their fooliſh heart be darkened, 'tis becauſe they liked not to retain God in their knowledge, though that which may be known of God is manifeſt in them. And if given up to believe a lie,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.10, 11.</note> tis for not receiving the love of the truth, but having pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, Theſe cauſes of Ignorance in Apoſtates from truth are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by the Scriptures, &amp; Primitive Doctrine. And if it hath been declared, you are not Condemned for what you know not, but for what you know and diſobey. It is to be underſtood only Comparatively,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30.</note> as in the places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove quoted; and that the time of Ignorance has been winked at. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, I know nothing by my ſelf (or I am not Conſcious) yet am I not hereby juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified. And <hi>Beza</hi> (no friend, but great Oppoſite,<note place="margin">Larger Notes.</note> to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts) on that place ſaith, This ſaying of <hi>Paul</hi> is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreined to a certain ſuppoſition; For Spirits both are to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172734:22"/>
be judged; and we ought to try our ſelves, whether we be in the Faith. Neither alſo doth the Apoſtle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn private Judgments of Charity; and much leſs ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Civil or Eccleſiaſtical Polity.</p>
            <p>But enough of this at this time (one may think) to bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance with a private uncharitable Judgment, that our Doctrin and Practice is Popiſh; without any other proof, but that <hi>W. R.</hi> is ſo perſwaded, he hath ſaid it and the people muſt pin their Faith on his ſleeve. His Authority is all, as all Authors; thereby he charges us virtually with them all in Groſs, in the lump. But let us ſee them ſingle, to be tryed, ſeeing herein we muſt be tryed by them; for as Erronious Doctrin muſt be tryed by the Scriptures, as they ſay, and Spirits by the Spirit; So Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery being that which came up under the Pope, and generally oppoſed by Proteſtants, can only be proved to be ſuch by their Authors.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Poſſevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus in Atheiſmis cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note>For <hi>Socinianiſm</hi> denying the divinity of Chriſt, a groſs Error, yet is not Popery. And Papiſts holding the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is not therefore Popery, but was before Popery, Truth. So herein he has alſo but expoſed himſelf an evil ſurmiſer to thoſe he has expoſed us to as ſuch.<note place="margin">Gault. on Jon. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> For whoſe ſake alſo this is, to prevent the poiſon of prejudice and jealouſy, than which nothing is more fallacious and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt,<note place="margin">Arg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on iſt. ein Schalck. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> according to the <hi>German</hi> Proverb. To which agrees the Greek verſ. ſignifying that
<q>
                  <p>More deviliſh ſlanders ariſe from thoughts than deeds.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Proverb. 18.17.</hi>
                     </bibl> He that is firſt in his own Cauſe ſeemeth juſt, but his Neighbour cometh, and ſearcheth him.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A lover of Truth, <hi>R. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
